Clearly violating fire code here.
显然违反了这里的消防法规。
I guess you can kind of maybe sit up there up front or you sit on the floor.
我想你可以坐在前面，也可以坐在地板上，
Right, so a lot to talk about,
好的，所以有很多话要说，
first of all, we have a DJ again, DJ 2PL,
首先，我们又有了一位 DJ ， 2PL ，
your the fiercest DJ is in jail right now,
你们凶猛的 DJ 现在在监狱里，
do you want to do a quick preview,
你想不想做个快速演示，
do it everyone.
为大家来一个。
All right, another big announcement too is that,
另一个重要的宣布是，
for the first time we now have two faculty teaching,
我们第一次有了两名导师，
Jignesh Patel is in the front row here,
Jingnesh Patel 坐在这里的前排，
Wisconsin,
威斯康星州，
we're happy that he's here,
我们很高兴他在这里，
so he'll be help me throughout the lecture.
所以他将在整个讲座中帮助我。
Okay, so, as I post on Piazza,
好的，正如我在 Piazza 上发布的那样，
there's another course lecture,
我们还有另一门课程，
they get Mooshoo out of jail,
他们让 Mooshoo 出狱，
of the course,
当然，
so we're not going to go over like a bunch of those things all over again,
所以我们不会像一堆这样的事情再来一次，
I just want to cover some things that if you might have missed,
我只想覆盖一些你可能会错过的事情，
that are important to understand throughout this lecture,
在整门课中要理解的重要内容，
and then we'll jump right into the material.
然后我们将直接进入材料。
All right, so the first thing,
好的，那么第一件事，
we have a course sponsor SingleStore,
我们有一个课程赞助商 SingleStore ，
cloud based database system,
基于云的数据库系统，
that supports sort of hybrid workloads transactions analytics,
支持混合工作负载事务分析，
as I said in the first lecture,
正如我在第一节课中所说，
it is a in memory column store,
它是一个内存中的列存储，
that uses skip list with just in time query,
使用跳过列表和即时查询，
distribute, share nothing,
分发，什么都不分享，
if none of that means anything to you right now, that's fine things,
如果现在这些对你来说没有任何意义，那也没关系，
coming at the end of the semester to give a guest lecture,
本学期末有一场客座讲座，
for a long time, the, you can call it MemSQL
很长时间，你可以称它为 MemSQL ，
and then they change the name to SingleStore,
然后他们将其更名为 SingleStore ，
it, so it's, it's a state of the art database system,
这是一个最先进的数据库系统，
that's going to cover,
它将涵盖，
that's going to incorporate a lot of the ideas that we'll discuss throughout the semester.
将与我们在整个学期讨论的大量想法有关。
The crowd is huge, obviously not everyone,
人群很多，显然不是每个人，
if you hear you're trying to got the wait list,
如果你听说，你想要得到等待名单，
the bad news is because the wait list is so huge,
坏消息是，等待名单太大了，
the department took it away from us
部门把它从我们手中拿走了，
and we have no control over it,
我们无法控制它，
they're trying to figure out,
他们试图弄清楚，
like who needs to graduate,
比如谁需要毕业，
who is to get the system elective and all that stuff,
谁将获得系统选修课，以及所有这些东西，
so if you come and ask us,
所以如果你来问我们，
hey, can they get off the wait list,
嘿，他们能从等待名单上除名吗，
the bad news is that we we don't control it anymore,
坏消息是，我们我们不再控制它了，
the good news is, because we have Jignesh now,
好消息是，因为我们现在有了 Jignesh ，
that will be teaching this class once every every semester,
他将每学期教一次这门课，
so if you can't get in this semester,
所以，如果你这学期进不去，
you'll be able to get it next semester
下个学期你就能拿到，
and then the admins will move people off the wait list
然后管理员会把人们从等待名单上移走，
as as people drop and that's become available.
因为人们下降了，这个可以了。
apartments,
地方，
things I found out since the [] faculty.
我从[]教员那里发现的东西。
So again, the first of the bad news is,
所以，第一个坏消息是，
if you're not enrolled now,
如果你现在没有注册，
you're unlike it again in the Spring.
你会在春天变得不同。
All right, for all this, the the important announcements,
好的，尽管如此，重要的公告，
everything will be in Piazza,
一切都将在 Piazza 上，
project zero, we should talk about less in the first lecture,
项目0 ，我们应该在第一堂课中少讲一些，
that's now available on Gradescope and on the website,
现在可以在 Gradescope 和网站上看到，
the final grades we show through Canvas,
我们通过 Canvas 展示的期末成绩，
and everything will be submitted through Gradescope,
所有的东西都将通过 Gradescope 提交，
again because people watch these lectures that aren't at CMU,
再次，因为人们在 CMU 外面观看这些课程，
they outside of our university,
他们在我们的大学外面，
if you want to test your projects beyond the same way that the way CMU students are,
如果你想用和 CMU 学生一样的方式测试你的项目，
there's a separate Gradescope account you can go to using that code there
你可以去一个单独的 Gradescope 账户，使用那里的代码，
and you can start them and, and test things out
你可以开始测试，然后测试，
and we'll release those projects as.
我们会发布这些项目。
So in exchange for, people to watch this,
作为看到这些的人们的交换，
in making this all available to you,
在向你提供这一切的过程中，
we need some,
我们需要一些，
I don't think you have one yet, do you,
我想你还没有，
mine got banned,
我的被禁了，
because the first about there, that is sort of true,
因为第一个在某种程度上是真的，
but they said I was born in the streets of Baltimore,
但他们说我出生在巴尔的摩的街头，
I am from Baltimore,
我来自巴尔的摩，
so whatever, and someone could finish that,
不管怎样，总有人能把它做完，
that would be great.
那太好了。
And I did, right,
我做了，
I comment, hey, I am, I am not from just not from the streets.
我评论说，嘿，我不是从街头来的。
So, to cover for logistics,
所以，为了覆盖后勤，
this is a big class,
这是一个大班，
obviously, there's a lot of people here that may have different backgrounds,
显然，这里有很多人可能有不同的背景，
and so we want you to interrupt us
所以我们希望你们能打断我们，
as we're going throughout the semester,
因为我们整个学期都在，
if questions about talking about, that's a fine question.
如果谈论关于[]的问题，那是很好的问题。
I also get very excited when I talk about again,
我也很兴奋谈到这个，
my life, wife, biological daughter, number one,
我的生活，我的妻子，我的亲生女儿，是第一的，
is databases and then nothing else,
还有数据库，然后什么都没有，
like I don't talk about hobbies,
比如我不谈论爱好，
it literally is just databases, confirm, it is just databases,
从字面上看，这只是数据库，确认这只是数据库，
yes, my parents are Trump supporters,
是的，我的父母是特朗普的支持者，
we don't talk to them,
我们不讨论这个，
like like it is just databases,
它只是数据库，
it's funny to you, right.
你们觉得很好笑。
So again, so if fast or if you have questions interrupt us,
再说一次，如果速度快，或者如果你有问题，打断我们，
what we're not going to do is that,
我们不会做的是，
at at the end of the class,
在课程结束时，
have people line up and say, what about slide five,
让大家排成一排，问幻灯片 5 怎么样，
the material we discussed during the lecture as we go along,
我们在讲课中讨论的材料，
because want you to interrupt as, as, as we're talking,
因为我想让你们打断我们，
because if you have questions and somebody else is likely have questions too,
因为如果你们有问题，其他人也可能有问题，
for us to these things and discuss it,
让我们来讨论这些事情，
and from a pedagogical standpoint,
从教育学的角度来看，
it's better for us as well,
这对我们也更好，
because I go back and watch
因为我会回去看，
and I see where people ask questions
我看到人们在哪里提问，
and I see, oh, that didn't get quite right, go fix the slot,
我看到，哦，这不太对劲，去解决问题，
so having the questions.
所以有问题。
All right, any questions about these logistics?
好的，对这些后勤有什么问题吗？
So let go right into it.
所以，让我们直奔主题。
Okay, so we gonna talk about sort of,
好的，所以我们要谈的是，
around what databases are, why it's important,
围绕什么是数据库，为什么它很重要，
why we need database management systems,
为什么我们需要数据库管理系统，
why this course exists,
为什么这门课会存在，
not just because we do stupid [Niche],
不仅是因为我们做了愚蠢的 Niche ，
it's, it's a super important topic
这是一个非常重要的话题，
and then we'll talk about the,
然后我们会讨论，
in my opinion, the the dominant model for how you want to build or use in in a database,
在我看来，在数据库中如何构建或使用的主要模型，
then let's talk about relational algebra,
然后让我们讨论关系型代数，
the mechanism or the operators we use to interact with a relational model database
我们用来与关系模型数据库交互的机制或运算符，
and we finish up,
我们结束，
because we have to be talking about alternative models,
因为我们必须讨论替代模型，
that people to evolutional model
人们发展模型，
and I have strong opinions of why they're wrong, okay?
我对为什么他们错了有强烈的看法，好吗？
All right, so, the second most important thing in my life.
好的，数据库是我生命中第二重要的事情。
Yes.
是的。
Yes, the question is, if you're on the wait list,
是的，问题是，如果你在等待名单上，
can you get access to Piazza,
你能进入 Piazza 吗，
yes, we'll post the, we make that available, yes.
是的，我们让它变得可用。
So here's a SQL server in the back,
所以这有 SQL server ，
MySQL, yes,
MySQL ，是的，
anybody one more, anybody,
还有没有人知道，
Cassandra, okay.
Cassandra ，好的。
Thing everybody listed, SQL server, Postgres, Mongo,
所有人列出的 SQL server, Postgres, mongo ，
those all database management systems, right,
这些都是数据库管理系统，
we're talking about databases,
我们谈论的是数据库，
and don't feel bad,
不要感到难过，
that not the only one making this mistake,
因为不是唯一一个犯这个错误的人，
this is Jeff, but I think this year,
这是 Jeff ，我想是今年，
see if it plays,
看看能不能播放，
tech beat for four, please,
科技挑战，谢谢，
a relational one of these systems presents the information to be stored and retrieved in rows and columns,
这些系统中的一个关系型系统以行和列的形式提供要存储和检索的信息，
Justin,
Justin ，
what is the matrix,
是不是矩阵，
no.
不是。
It'll get worse, okay, right,
情况会变得更糟，好的，
database not, again being pedantic here,
数据库不是，再次这里是迂腐的，
but it's good to understand the distinction between the two,
但理解两者之间的区别是很好的，
because when we just talk about the data models,
因为当我们只谈论数据模型时，
you don't understand,
你不会理解，
like, okay, we don't care about system implement yet about what data actually is
好吧，我们还不关心系统实现，数据实际上是什么，
and how we're going to interact with it.
以及我们将如何与它交互。
So, organized collection of data that's related to each other,
所以，有组织的相互关联的数据集合，
that's meant to model some aspects,
这意味着对某些方面进行建模，
everybody lives systems,
每个人都在系统中生活，
an example of a database that would be the university database,
一个数据库的例子是大学的数据库，
that keeps track of what students are enrolled in what classes and your grades, right,
跟踪哪些学生注册了哪些班级和你的成绩，
because that's trying to model, you know, the real university interactions
因为这是在试图模拟真实的大学互动，
that that students are taking classes and getting paid.
学生们上课并获得回报。
This course is so important,
这门课程非常重要，
because the database, a database, is going to be the fundamental component,
因为数据库将是基础组件，
the underlying of any application
任何应用程序的基础，
or anything you're going to do with the rest of your life,
或者任何你将在你的余生中做的事情，
so matter of like if you're a CS student,
所以，如果你是一名 CS 学生，
no matter if you go off and get a job doing and in doing CS related things
无论你去做了一份与 CS 相关的工作，
or you you don't, do, you know you're not not a programmer,
或者你不是程序员，
at the end of the day, you're always going to be interacting with the database,
归根结底，你将始终与数据库交互，
even if if it's an Excel spreadsheet database,
即使它是 Excel 电子表格数据库，
is one.
是其中之一。
And this course is important,
这门课程很重要，
because because you're going to end up interacting with database systems,
因为你最终将与数据库系统交互，
you need to understand what's actually get inside,
你需要了解其中实际包含的内容，
even if, if, if it's a small application like running in your cell phone
即使是在手机上运行的小应用程序，
or a application with gigabytes of data,
或者有大量数据的应用程序，
it's important to understand queries,
理解查询也是很重要的，
or when you see database system, what does it actually.
或者当你看数据库系统时，它实际上是什么。
And what are the tradeoffs you would make
你会做出哪些权衡，
for how you use one data model versus another,
在使用一种数据模型与另一种数据模型，
or one database approach versus another.
或一种数据库与另一种数据库。
What's the most widely deployed database system in the world,
世界上部署最广泛的数据库系统是什么，
you might take a guess,
你可以猜猜看，
everyone has a cell phone, right,
每个人都有一部手机，
SQLite is on every single cell phone
每一部手机上都有 SQLite ，
and it's written by one dude down in north Carolina,
它是由北卡罗来纳州的一个家伙写的，
kind, but like helper doesn't have an address,
但帮手没有地址，
he's like, he's like a nomad.
他就像一个游牧民族。
So let's an example of a database,
让我们举一个数据库的例子，
we talk about university application,
我们讨论了大学应用，
we talk about something more relevant to everyone here,
我们谈论一些与这里的每个人更相关的事情，
same thing like Spotify or like Bandcamp or Itunes or KeepMusic.
与 Spotify Bandcamp iTunes 或 KeepMusic 类似的东西。
So we can create a really simple database,
所以我们可以创建一个非常简单的数据库，
that has basically two entities,
它有两个实体，
there's artists appear on albums.
有艺人出现在专辑中。
So the thing we need to store in our data is gonna be,
所以我们需要存储在我们的数据中的东西是，
like for every single artist,
比如对于每个艺术家，
yeah, what's their name, what country did they start,
他们的名字是什么，他们是从哪个国家开始的，
and the album could be like,
专辑可能是这样的，
what's the name of the album, when did it come out,
专辑的名字是什么，它是什么时候推出的，
what artists appear on it.
有哪些艺术家出现在里面。
And so, what we talk about now
所以，我们现在讨论的是，
we do a sort of strawman implementation of a database, database
一个数据库的稻草人实现，
and we'll see why it's stupid
我们将看到为什么它是愚蠢的，
and we see all the problems that it's going to have,
我们会看到它将会有的所有问题，
and then that again that'll help motivate
然后，这将有助于激励，
why we actually want to build a full fledged database,
我们为什么想要建立一个成熟的数据库，
or rely on a full fledged database.
或者依赖一个成熟的数据库。
So the easiest way to implement a database system that manages data is
所以，实现管理数据的数据库系统的最简单方法是，
to just use files on disk, right,
只使用磁盘上的文件，
so for every single,
所以对于每个，
for my two entities, I have an Album, I have an Artist,
对于我的两个实体， Album 和 Artist ，
I have a csv file, comma separated value file,
我有一个 CSV 文件，逗号分隔值文件，
and every single in that file, that every single line, right,
那份文件里的每一行，
I want to find in my,
我想要在我的[]找到[]，
I'm going to open it up, you know, parse it, line my line
我要打开它，解析它，排成一行，
and try to find the data that I'm looking for, right.
试着找到我正在寻找的数据。
So say I want to do something,
所以，假设我想做一件事，
versus the csv magic word parts,
对于 CSV 魔法词的部分，
basically just splitting on the commas,
就是用逗号分开，
then if I find that the the name of the,
然后如果我发现这个名字是 (GZA) ，
then I print it out.
然后我把它打印出来。
All right, it works,
好的，它起作用了，
but this is bad, why?
但这很糟糕，为什么？
Yes.
好的。
It's gone really, really slow member increases.
它会变得非常缓慢，随着成员的增加。
Yeah, so always to think of in extremes in, in software,
是的，所以在软件中总是要考虑极端的情况，
three records here,
这里有三条记录，
yeah, I can load that up in a single page and parse that pretty quickly,
是的，我可以将它加载到一个页面中，并很快进行解析，
but if I have 3 billion records,
但如果我有 30 条记录，
then yeah, and if GZA is the last, the last entry,
而且如果 GZA 是最后一个条目，
then I gotta parse every single line by line.
那么我必须逐行解析每一个条目。
Yes.
好的。
She says that the insertion deletion would be really horrible given the system restrictions,
她说，考虑到系统的限制，插入删除将非常可怕，
so insertion wouldn't be that bad, right,
所以插入不会那么糟糕，
because if I just append to the end of it, who cares, right.
因为如果我只是附加到它的末尾，谁会在乎呢。
Right, so she said, what if I keep things sorted by release year,
是的，她说，如果我按发行年份分类，会怎么样，
then, yeah, I have to go find where it should be,
那么，是的，我得去找它应该在哪里，
that would suck,
那会很糟糕，
you also said update or delete, right,
你也说过更新或删除，
if I want to delete entry,
如果我想删除条目，
I get it's the same problem as looking for
我会得到与查找相同的问题，
and I got to find the thing I'm looking for and delete it.
我必须找到正在寻找的东西并将其删除。
Those are [] issues,
这些都是[]问题，
but there are some other problems as well.
但还有一些其他问题。
So your statement is that,
所以你的说法是，
I'm representing everything as, say, strings,
我把所有的东西都表示为，比如说，字符串，
and then if there's a what.
然后如果有什么。
Yeah, correct,
是的，没错，
yeah, so her comment is,
所以她的说法是，
I'm, I'm so in the years in this case is text file,
我在这种情况下 year 是文本文件，
so it's ASCII text,
所以它是 ASCII 文本，
but my magic parse function, which I haven't defined,
但我的魔术解析函数，我还没有定义，
is somehow knowing, oh, this should be an integer
不知何故知道，哦，这应该是一个整数，
and it's going to call atoi,
它将调用 atoi ，
it's going to cast the, the varchar into, the string to an integer,
它将把字符串成一个整数，
and it the best,
而且它是最好的，
if it's just a bunch of files on disk,
如果它只是磁盘上的一堆文件，
a parsing error, you're corrupt,
一个解析错误，就崩溃了，
that's a good one.
这是个好想法。
What are some other problems?
还有其他一些问题吗？
You say reading, writing the file,
你说读取，写入文件，
we sort of covered that, right,
我们在某种程度上涵盖了这些，
if you're inserting the end, no big deal,
如果你要插入到尾部，没什么问题，
reading, could it could me well?
读取，能够很好吗？
We said a comment in the name might break,
我们说过，名字中的一条评论可能会破坏，
the like python packages for that.
这点类似 Python 包。
Yes.
好的。
Yeah, you said you're not allowed to have current use of the file,
是的，你说你不能使用这份文件，
the writer as things get a little dicey, yeah.
写入作为字符串有点危险，是的。
Yeah.
是的。
of the the file,
文件中，
the scheme of the correlation of the database is implicitly,
数据库的关联方案是隐式的，
we'll see that in the second.
我们一会儿会看到。
So we covered these, right.
所以我们覆盖了这些。
So how to ensure that,
所以，我如何确保，
going back real quickly.
很快返回。
Right, so I have [],
是的，所以，我有[]，
but I'm gonna fix it,
但我会修好它的,
I got to make sure that every single place where I have,
我要确保我所拥有的每一行，
so it all gets updated the same,
所以所有的更新同时发生，
these are on disk,
它们是在磁盘上，
the operating system or the file system doesn't know,
操作系统或文件系统不知道，
it just knows that, you know, whatever you want to read,
它只知道，你想读什么，
so we now in the application to go,
所以我们现在在应用程序，
we make sure all the entries will we [].
我们要确保所有的条目都会[]。
She brought up the issue,
她提出了一个问题，
of what if someone ever writes a year with invalid string,
如果有人用无效字符串写入 year ，
we'd throw a parsing error,
我们会抛出一个解析错误，
in my example here, I only have,
在我的示例中，我只有，
I'm assuming there's a one one correspondence between,
我假设两者之间有一对一的对应关系，
album could only have one artist,
专辑只能有一个艺术家，
but obviously we know that's not the case
但显然我们知道情况并非如此，
and a lot of albums,
很多专辑都是如此，
so how do I go change my files now to account for that,
那么，我现在如何更改我的文件以说明这一点呢，
lead artist who has albums,
拥有专辑的首席艺人，
right, well, in my example here, nothing will happen,
在我的例子中，什么都不会发生，
and now I got a bunch of albums
现在我有一堆专辑，
that have an artist's name, that doesn't map anything to,
其中的艺术家的名字没有任何匹配，
so the reference integrity gets broken.
所以，基准完整性被破坏。
We brought a lot of implementation issues already,
我们已经带来了很多实现问题，
like how do you find,
比如你如何查找，
in my example here, it's it's O(n), right,
在我的例子中，它是 O(n) ，
I have to do a brute force scan, scan across the entire file
我必须对整个文件进行穷举扫描，
to find the thing I'm looking for,
才能找到我正在寻找的东西，
now if I assume that there,
现在如果我假设在那里，
only one person that you know only went out with a given name,
只有一个人有给定的名字，
then I can stop, because I'm done,
然后我就可以停下来，因为我已经完成了，
the same name all the time,
一直都是同一个名字，
albums that I don't know GZA puts out,
那张专辑 GZA 找出来，
like, like GZA in Florida or something like that,
比如佛罗里达州的 GZA 或类似的，
I got to keep scanning the entire file,
我得继续扫描整个文件，
and that's going to be n or order of n.
这将是 n 或 [n 阶]。
My example here, again, I have that's, that's operating in the files,
我的例子，再一次，那是在文件中运行的，
but let's say I want to rewrite it to now run,
但是假设我想重写它，现在运行，
I want to want to write a new application that uses the same database,
我想要编写一个使用相同数据库的新应用程序，
but I want to write it in Rust,
但我想使用 Rust 编写，
because that's the hot thing,
因为这是最热门的东西，
so now I've got to go make sure that,
现在我必须确保，
whatever information or implicit scheme I had in my Python code
我的 Python 代码中的任何信息或隐式方案
now maps over to my Rust code,
现在都映射到了我的 Rust 代码，
but then now if my files change,
但是，如果我的文件发生了更改，
I've got to make sure I go change both the Python code and the Rust code,
我必须确保同时更改了 Python 代码和 Rust 代码，
maybe, say the guy wrote the Python code, you know, is in jail
也许，比如，写 Python 代码的这个家伙在监狱里，
and we can't update it, right,
我们无法更新它，
now, what do I do,
现在，我该怎么办，
going to break.
快要崩溃了。
What if the app even on the same machine,
如果这个应用程序即使在同一台机器上，
where my Python code is running, right,
我的 Python 代码运行的机器，
running like a microservice on a on a separate box,
比如作为一个单独的机器上的微服务运行，
how do I get access to that other,
我如何访问另一个，
how do I get access to that file.
我如何才能访问那个文件。
And then, what happens if you have two threads trying to write to the same file, the same,
然后，如果你有两个线程试图写入相同的文件，
well, you can rely on the operating system to do,
好的，你可以依靠操作系统来做，
but again, if I have a billion records
但同样的，如果我有 10 亿条记录，
and I want to update one of them,
我想要更新其中的一条记录，
don't want to lock a billion billion records,
不想锁定 10 亿条记录，
just do that one up,
只需更新这条记录，
ideally, when I fill more fine grain,
理想情况下，当我完成更多的细粒度时，
that can have multiple threads.
可以有多个线程。
How to make sure that our data is safe, if there's a crash,
如果发生崩溃，如何确保我们的数据安全，
and then I crash before fsync,
然后我在 fsync 之前崩溃了，
some of that data actually might have gotten that disk,
其中一些数据可能已经到了那张磁盘，
so when my, my,
所以当我的，
I must twice,
我必须再来一次，
which is not what I want, right,
这不是我想要的，
because now I've corrupted data,
因为现在我破坏了数据，
or now my database is is really big
或者现在我的数据库真的很大，
and I have a lot of people want to access it,
有很多人想访问它，
how do I make sure that I can duplicate and replicate across multiple machines,
我如何确保可以跨多台计算机进行复制，
so they can all service reads at the same,
以便它们可以同时为所有读取提供服务，
so my application can scale up,
这样我的应用程序就可以向上扩展，
files aren't going to do that for me.
文件不会帮我做到这一点。
So this is just a quick smattering of database management system, right,
所以这只是数据库管理系统的一小部分，
and why a course like this, in my opinion.
在我看来，为什么会有这门课。
So as our database management system is going to be
所以，作为我们的数据库管理系统是，
the the software that can allow applications to store and analyze information in a database,
允许应用程序在数据库中存储和分析信息的软件，
and ideally not have to worry about all the things that we just talked about,
理想情况下，不必担心我们刚刚谈到的所有事情，
that's not always been the case,
但情况并不总是这样，
there's many trade offs to the,
这其中有很多取舍，
you know, guarantees in exchange for performance,
[保证]换来的是性能，
and a general purpose system typically allow you
而通用系统通常允许你，
to adjust you know, what those tradeoffs actually are.
调整这些权衡是什么。
And so a, the, the database management system is going to define or specify [] implementation
所以，数据库管理系统将定义或指定实现，
and how you can go create databases,
如何创建数据库，
how you can query them,
如何查询数据库，
how you can changes, you can administer the databases,
如何更改，如何管理数据库，
making, making changes and other things,
进行更改以及其他事情，
insert a correspondence of some kind of data model.
插入某种数据模型的对应关系。
Well, I say also too that this is again,
我也要再次说，
you no matter whether you go off and actually build database systems,
不管你是否真的去构建数据库系统，
you know in in your day to day job,
在你的日常工作中，
this is to be, its important again to know where you go,
这是很重要的，知道你去哪里，
because at some point, you're gonna be some build some application,
因为在某个时候，你会构建一些应用程序，
you have to decide what database management system I want to use
你必须决定我想要使用哪种数据库管理系统，
and that should always be sort the first choice,
这应该始终是你的第一选择，
that like you don't want to do my, but here,
如果不想做我在这里的[]，
a lot of problems.
有很多问题。
I was like, do you, think you like at a startup,
想象你在一家创业公司，
and you're trying to build an application, a application,
你尝试构建一个应用程序，
startup doesn't have a lot of money,
初创公司没有很多钱，
your your your stressed or time to try to get things out the door
你有压力，也没有时间试着把东西拿出来，
to get the first version out the door,
把第一个版本推出来，
do you really want to be spending your time making sure that
你真的想花时间确保
your data is safe and there's is a crash,
你的数据是安全的，当发生崩溃时，
because in the end, that's not a distinguishing feature of your business or your application,
因为归根结底，这并不是你的业务或应用程序的一个显著特征，
nobody cares that if you actually lose data,
没有人关心，如果你真的丢失了数据，
that you so if you crash, you don't lose data,
所以如果你崩溃了，你不会丢失数据，
that's considered like you know, this point in in modern computing systems
这样考虑，在现代计算系统中，
and so rather than spending all this time trying to rent your own bespoke database system,
所以，与其花费所有时间试图租用你自己的定制数据库系统，
you should just use something up,
你应该只用一些上面的东西，
chances are, it probably progress,
变更是可能的，
and out of a hundred,
在一百种情况下，
that that's the first choice you should use,
这是你应该使用的第一选择，
maybe SQLite,
也许是 SQLite ，
but Postgres will get you pretty far,
但 Postgres 会让你走得很远，
that I'm talking about here.
我在这里说的。
So again, a data model is going to be, again,
再次，数据模型将是，
how we're going to represent entities or the collection of data in our database,
我们将如何表示数据库中的实体或数据集合，
so, so the data model is this high level abstraction,
所以，数据模型就是这种高级抽象，
specifies how we represent individual entities and potentially that relate to,
指定我们如何表示各个实体以及可能与之相关的[]，
and again, we're trying to model some aspect of the real world,
再次，我们试图对真实世界的某些方面进行建模，
students take classes, students are get grades,
学生上课，学生拿到成绩，
they're in their home department.
他们在自己的内政部门。
And then the schema is going to represent the, the definition or the description of the,
然后，模式将表示、定义或描述，
of what those entities in our data model of our database look like,
我们的数据库数据模型中的这些实体是什么样子，
student names, you have have birth dates, have email addresses and so forth,
学生姓名，有出生日期，电子邮件地址等等，
you would specify all of those in our schema,
你将在我们的模式中指定所有这些，
and then we, we would instantiate instances of a database
然后我们将根据该模式实例化，
based on a data model according to the schema.
基于数据模型的数据库实例。
So there's a bunch of different data models that are out there,
市场上有很多不同的数据模型，
so this goes, this goes back to the very beginning of databases,
这可以追溯到数据库的最开始，
people sort of realize, oh, we need a is in, is in a database.
人们意识到，我们需要一个在数据库中。
So most systems today,
今天的大多数系统，
something that looks like like the relational databases, relational relational data model,
看起来像关系数据库，关系关系数据模型，
there's things called object relational,
有一种叫做对象关系，
Postgres is it just means you can have user defined types
Postgres 是意味着你可以用用户定义的类型
to extend what your relations are,
来扩展你的关系，
but at a high level, most data systems are going be relational.
但在高层次上，大多数数据系统都将是关系型的，
I think there's that DB Engines the ranking that,
我认为那个 DB Engines 排名，
the most popular database,
最流行的数据库，
I think the four out of the five most popular databases are going to be all relational,
我认为五个最流行的数据库中有四个都是关系型的，
mongo is, is the other.
Mongo 是其他的。
Then there's a bunch of these other data models,
然后还有一堆其他的数据模型，
that sort of fall under this umbrella term,
在某种程度上属于这个总括术语，
a thing of NoSQL systems,
一种 NoSQL 系统，
it usually the document data model or json one of these,
它通常是文档数据模型或 json 其中之一，
Cassandra, essentially become, has become one of these,
Cassandra 是其中之一，
but there's key value stores databases,
但有键值存储数据库，
and then what family is this sort of []?
然后[]类型的家族是什么？
There's array matrix and vector data data models,
有数组矩阵和矢量数据数据模型，
these are primarily used for machine learning or scientific applications,
它们主要用于机器学习或科学应用，
I think of like a satellite going around and taking a bunch of photos,
比如一颗卫星绕着拍了一大堆照片，
you could store that as an array,
你可以将其存储为数组，
tensors to train some kind of model,
训练某种模型的张量，
you would represent that as as well,
你也会把它表示为[]，
and so there's specialized database that can represent natively represent array.
所以有专门的数据库可以表示原生的数组。
And then these ones at the end for old people,
然后这些最后的是为以前的人，
hierarchical, network and multi-value,
分层，网络和多值，
these are considered obsolete at this point,
现在，这些被认为是过时的，
since I still make a lot of money use each,
因为我每一次都能赚很多钱，
the hierarchical model is used in IMS,
分层模型在 IMS 中使用，
IBM first database system that they built,
IBM 构建的第一个数据库系统，
of all the parts for the [], 1960,
所有[]的组成部分，在 1960 年代，
every ATM basically uses,
每个 ATM 都使用，
I mean not, not the box itself,
我的意思是不是盒子本身，
when when you communicate to the bank,
而是当你与银行沟通时，
a lot of these systems are using IMS,
很多这些系统都在使用 IMS ，
social security in the US government still uses IMS.
美国社会保障部仍在使用 IMS 。
And so, so these things exist,
所以，这些东西是存在的，
but if you're brand new,
但如果你是全新的，
you're not, you're not gonna say I'm going to use IMS
你不会说我会使用 IMS ，
or I'm, I'm gonna use IMS,
或我将使用 IMS ，
like you'd be insane to do that,
你要是那样做肯定是疯了，
but again, not at all,
但是再次，不用管，
it's not really relevant here.
它在这里并不相关。
Right, for this course,
在本课程中，
some databases in the relational data model.
关系数据模型中的一些数据库。
And this is why I was pissed all about the [] thing,
这就是为什么我对[]的事情很生气，
because we go back to it,
因为我们回到这里，
Justin. The judges have reviewed your response of matrix in the Tech beat category
Justin ，评委审查了你在科技挑战类别中的矩阵的回答，
and they have decided that it is correct,
他们认为这是正确的，
we've added 800 dollars to your score
我们已经在你的分数上增加了 800 美元，
and all of your wagers were made on the adjusted score.
你所有的赌注都是在调整后的分数上进行的。
There is no such thing as a relational matrix,
没有关系矩阵这回事，
I sent them an email they didn't respond.
我给他们发了一封电子邮件，他们没有回应。
Anyway, got a PhD,
无论如何，拿到博士学位，
I think it's like neuroscience,
我认为这就像神经科学，
but like, you know, whatever.
但就像，随便什么。
So hopefully, if nothing else in this course,
所以希望，如果这门课没有其他内容，
you can answer that question.
你可以回答这个问题。
So let's go back to the 1960s
让我们回到 1960 年代，
and this again motivate why the relational model came about,
这再次激发了为什么关系模型的产生，
and it'll set us up for why it's still prevalent
它将为我们建立为什么它仍然流行，
and why the use today,
为什么今天的仍在使用，
[] it for any new.
对于任何新的。
Back in the 1960s, early 1960s,
回到 1960 年代早期，
there wasn't a relational model, wasn't relational databases,
没有关系模型，没有关系数据库，
it wasn't Postgres, it wasn't MySQL SQLite model, right,
也没有 Postgres MySQL SQLite 模型，
the first day, there is people were building were not meant really, meant to be general purpose,
最开始，人们构建的不是通用的，
but then they realize,
但是他们意识到，
oh, instead of building these bespoke database applications or database systems for just this one application,
哦，不是只为这一个应用程序构建这些定制的数据库应用程序或数据库系统，
I can make a bit more general
我可以做得更通用一些，
and and now I can support any possible application,
现在我可以支持任何可能的应用程序，
so as far as, you know, the first database system ever existed,
目前，第一个存在的数据库系统，
but Built by General Electric,
是由通用电气构建的，
which then then sold to Honeywell 1960s,
后来被出售给霍尼韦尔 1960 年代，
with IDS they originally built to keep, in Seattle,
他们最初构建的 IDS 是为了保留[]，在西雅图，
and then they realize, oh, instead of building this just for the,
然后他们意识到，哦，不只是为了[]，
we can make some tweaks, and then make it,
我们可以做一些调整，然后使它，
so paper company could use it or, or a phone company could use it,
这样我们造纸公司就可以使用它，或者电话公司可以使用它，
and that sort of became one of the first general purpose database systems that ever built.
这可以说是有史以来最早的通用数据库系统之一。
Oh, we could use this for other applications,
哦，我们可以把它用在其他应用程序上，
and they generalized it.
他们推广了它。
And then CODASYL is a standards that defined late 1960s or 1970s,
而 CODASYL 是一种标准，定义于六十年代末或七十年代，
as a way to, as an interact way to interact with database systems,
作为一种与数据库系统交互的方式，
people realize, instead of having these standard, these these,
人们意识到，与其拥有这些标准，
database systems that were being built at the time,
当时正在构建的数据系统，
we would have standardize way for how,
我们将有标准化的方式，
less than 5% or 5.
不到 5% 或 5% 。
I'm assuming you here are heard CODASYL.
我猜你在这里听到过 CODASYL 。
One, okay, so why,
一个，好的，那是为什么，
in the book, in the book, yeah.
在书里，在书里，是的。
People,
人们，
and in, in these early systems,
在这些早期系统中，
this is the way you would in interact with database systems,
这是你与数据库系统交互的方式，
and a lot of the things that were in inherent in these first implications
而在这些最初的影响中固有的许多事情
are things you would not want to do today,
是你今天不想做的事情，
so one of the big things was,
最重要的一件事是，
in these first systems,
在这些第一批系统中，
they had this tight coupling
它们有紧密的耦合，
between the logical layer, the schema, what what entities do I have, what are their attributes,
在逻辑层、模式，拥有什么实体、它们的属性，
and then a physical layer in the system,
以及系统中的物理层之间，
meaning, like, how is actually being represented on disk or in memory
这意味着，如何在磁盘或内存中表示，
and how would I actually interact with them, right.
以及我将如何与它们交互，
And so what happened is
发生的情况是，
if you, if you were a programmer at the time
如果你当时是一名程序员，
and you wanted to use one of these database systems,
你想要使用其中一个数据库系统，
you had to know exactly how the databases is storing your database,
你必须确切地知道数据库如何存储你的数据库，
and so because that would expose a different API to you to interact with it.
因为这将向你公开一个不同的 API 来与其交互。
Well, on IMS, you could store data is
在 IMS 上，你可以将数据存储为
either as a hash table or a B+ tree or tree structure
哈希表或 B+ 树或树结构，
and, and then you got different APIs,
然后你有不同的 API ，
because you know, depending on which data structure we're using,
因为，取决于我们使用的数据结构，
because hash tables, you can't do scans,
因为哈希表，你不能进行扫描，
but in tree structures.
但是在树形结构中（可以）。
So now the problem with this is that
所以，现在的问题是，
any single time I want to make a change to the schema at both the logical layer and the physical layer,
每当我想要同时更改逻辑层和物理层的模式时，
I had to go rewrite my application,
我都必须重写我的应用程序，
almost from scratch,
几乎是从头开始，
because oh, how the database was represented on disk changed,
因为，数据库在磁盘上的表示方式发生了变化，
other issues with the data model,
数据模型的其他问题，
we don't need really,
我们不需要真正的，
like in the, the, the higher model,
比如在更高的模型中，
you had to sort of have these for loops traverse,
你必须有循环遍历，
you know, one collection versus another collection,
一个集合与另一个集合，
it was really inefficient way, inefficient way to interact with the database system.
这是与数据库系统交互非常低效的方式。
What happened was in the late 1960s,
事情发生在 1960 年代末，
there was this guy, Ted Codd, who was,
有一个人， Ted Codd ，他是，
and he was walking up in, in, in New York, where the big lab is,
他来到纽约，[大实验室]所在地，
and he saw all these, these, these IBM developers primarily working,
他看到了所有这些 IBM 开发人员的主要工作，
saw them rewriting database applications over and over again,
看到他们一遍又一遍地重写数据库应用程序，
every single time there was a schema change,
每一次 schema 改变，
every single time was a physical layout change, right,
都是物理布局的改变，
humans were rapidly,
人类的反应很快，
so people, okay, yeah, we'll just walk humans at the problem
所以人们，我们只是把这个问题上给人类，
and, you know, and that's better than buying a,
这比买一个[]更好，
so my example, he pointed out,
所以，我的例子是，他指出，
embedded in my,
嵌入我的（例子），
so, name column,
所以， name 列，
we think of it now that was like the ID of artist,
现在把它当成艺术家的 ID ，
I had to go,
我必须，
a trivial example,
一个微不足道的例子，
but that was the kind of shit they were doing back in the day.
但这是他们以前做的那种垃圾。
So, Codd saw this and said there's, there's gotta be a better way
所以， Codd 看到这个，说一定有更好的方法，
and he model as an abstraction
他（构建）了一个模型作为抽象，
of how, how to represent the a database
关于如何表示数据库，
and the relationship between entities in and in a database
以及数据库中实体之间的关系，
and avoid having the tight coupling between physical layer and in the logical layer,
避免了物理层和逻辑层之间的紧密耦合，
meaning define it in mathematical terms,
意味着用数学术语定义它，
I had these relations,
我有这些关系，
here's the manipulations or changes or lookups I could do on them
这是我可以对它们进行的操作、更改或查找，
and I don't know, don't care,
我不知道，我不在乎，
how the database system underneath the covers is actually going to store it,
隐藏在幕后的数据库系统将如何存储这些数据，
because the data system knows what the data is,
因为数据系统知道数据是什么，
knows what the queries are,
知道查询是什么，
it can be a better position to decide how to,
所以它可以更好地决定如何（处理），
IBM first proposed the relational data model in 1969,
IBM 第一次提出关系数据模型是在 1969 年，
there's it's tech report paper.
这是一份科技报告。
And again, mathematician,
再说一次，数学家，
he didn't define programming language at the time,
他当时并没有定义编程语言，
he's not saying how you actually implement this,
他没有说你如何实现这一点，
he's just defining what ralational relations are
他只是在定义什么是关系，
and the algebra to manipulate them, right.
以及操纵它们的代数。
So there's three key tenets of, of,
所以，有三个关键的原则，
but these are three ones that were going to care about the most.
但这三个是受最关心的。
So, the first is that,
所以，第一个是，
we're going to store all our collection of data in simple data structures,
我们要存储所有的数据在简单的数据结构中，
that's the mathematical term, same thing as a table,
这是数学术语，和表格是一样的，
if you're coming from the Mongo world,
如果你来自 Mongo 世界，
they call it a collection, it's the same idea,
他们称之为 collection ，这是同样的想法，
all these simple data structures,
所有这些简单的数据结构，
I need worry about all membership sets,
我考虑所有的成员关系集，
that all these other data sets.
而不是所有其他的数据集。
Second is that,
第二个是，
you're going to keep the physical representation of the database itself,
你将保留物理表示在数据库本身，
like the actual bits and bytes on disk or in memory,
比如磁盘或内存中的实际位和字节，
you're going to leave that,
你将留着它，
you, not it, in your relational data model,
你不[]它在你的关系数据模型中，
leave that for the database system
把这个留给数据库系统，
and figure out what the best way to, right,
然后找出最好的方法，
because the idea now is maybe,
因为现在的想法可能是，
if I store the data one way,
如果我以一种方式存储数据，
but then as I see what kind of data I'm putting in,
但当我看到我要放入什么样的数据，
what kind of equipment, data sets aside,
把数据放入什么样的设备，
oh, I really want to store this on two machines or files
哦，我想把它存储在两台机器或文件上，
or or break it up in different ways or or sort it in one way,
或者用不同的方式拆分，或者用一种方式分类，
and again now your application doesn't change,
再次，现在你的应用程序没有改变，
because you're just writing things queries at a high at a high level,
因为你只是在很高的级别编写查询，
and you don't really care how underneath the covers, right,
你不会在乎在下面的情况，
and that's the here you're going to define, at a high level,
这就是你要在高级别上定义的，
you're going access data through a high level language
你将通过高级语言访问数据，
and then let the database system figure out
然后让数据系统找出，
what's the best way to, to retrieve the data that you're looking for,
检索你在寻找的数据的最佳方式，
do whatever operation you want to do.
做任何你想做的操作。
So, Codd won the Turing, won for this in 1981,
所以， Codd 在 1981 年获得了图灵奖，
[] he won it in like 72,
[]说他会在 72 岁获得，
but it took ten years for people to realize he was wrong,
但人们花了十年时间意识到他是错的.
until he won Turing awards,
直到他获得图灵奖，
Codd is dead,
Codd 去世了，
and then the, the other guy that won the the the Touring award in database, Jim Gray,
然后，在数据库中获得图灵奖的另一个人 Jim Gray ，
he got lost in [],
他获得[]，
and then the last, the Turing award in database is, is Michael Stonebraker and he's Postgres
最后，数据库中的获得图灵奖的是 Michael Stonebraker 和他的 Postgres ，
and was IBM advisor,
他是 IBM 的顾问，
well, we'll cover Stonebraker.
好的，我们会说到 Stonebraker 。
So there's three key aspects of the data model.
所以，数据模型有三个关键方面。
There's the structure that,
其中的结构是，
how we're going to, how we define what the data database actually is,
我们如何定义数据库是什么，
what what's in our relations,
我们的关系中有什么，
what are their attributes and the types.
它们的属性和类型是什么。
There's the integrity methods that
有一些完整性方法，
specify what data is allowed to be stored in the database, right,
指定允许将哪些数据存储在数据库中，
to make sure that you know every,
确保每一个，
email went wrong if records without an email address,
邮箱会出错，如果记录没有邮箱地址，
or in my example,
或者，在我的例子中，
I can't have an album,
我不能有一张专辑，
that has an artist that doesn't exist in the artist.
有一个不存在于 artist 表的艺术家。
And then the manipulation mechanisms allow us to define
然后，操纵机制允许我们定义，
how we're going to access the data and update data.
如何访问和更新数据，
And what about the last one was, what we'll talk about when we start talking about.
最后一个，我们在开始讨论的时候会讲到。
An unordered set of data,
一组无序数据，
that's going to contain the relationship of attributes that represent some entity in the real world,
将包含代表现实世界中某个实体的属性之间的关系，
so the model doesn't mean the relationship between tables,
所以，该模型并不意味着表之间的关系，
it's really the relationship between attributes,
它实际上是属性之间的关系，
within the table.
在表里面。
So again, a student has an email address,
所以，再次，学生有一个电子邮件地址，
they have a phone number,
他们有一个电话号码，
a birthday, home address, right,
一个生日，一个家庭地址，
that relation of those attributes combined together to represent some.
这些属性组合在一起的关系代表了一些（学生）。
So again, so we'll have a set of attributes,
所以，我们将拥有一组属性，
I'll use the word tuple,
我会用 tuple 这个词，
but it also you mean record or row,
但它也意味着记录或列，
again at a high level, they all mean the same way, same thing.
在更高的级别上，它们的意思都是一样的。
And so for the, for every single in the original definition of the relational data model,
所以，对于关系数据模型的原始定义中的每一个，
all the values have to be atomic or scalar,
所有值都必须是原子值或标量值，
but again, as things have evolved over time,
但是再次，随着时间的推移，事情发生了变化，
again, Codd didn't foresee these things back in the 70s,
Codd 在 70 年代没有预见到这些事情，
this is,
这是，
support this today.
今天支持这一点。
And of course, all to be there,
当然，所有都在那里，
so we can, in some cases,
所以我们可以，在某些情况下，
a, some attributes could have a value that is NULL,
某些属性的值可能为空，
meaning it's unknown at the time,
这意味着它在当时是未知的，
and again, you can specify in the schema whether you want an to support.
而且你可以在模式中指定是否希望支持。
So in every relation,
所以在每个关系中，
there's going to be a primary key,
都会有一个主键，
that's going to be used to uniquely identify a tuple,
它将被用来唯一标识一个 tuple ，
again, think of like your student ID, your Andrew ID here at the university,
想象一下你的学生证，你在大学里的 Andrew ID ，
that allows us to know exactly, you know,
这让我们可以确切地知道，
or record that we want,
或者我们想要的记录，
when we're doing.
当我们操作的时候。
Example here,
这里有个例子，
particular, particular entry in our database,
我们数据库中的特定条目，
but your Andrew ID is unique
但是你的 Andrew ID 是唯一的，
and that so that would be a primary for the university database.
所以，这是大学数据库的主键。
What you can do in cases, where you don't have primary,
在你没有的主键情况下，你能做些什么，
identity column,
标识列，
the primary key.
主键。
You see this a lot in ORM,
你会在 ORM 中看到很多这个，
if you like SQLite, if you're using NodeJS,
比如 SQLite ，如果你使用的是 NodeJS ，
a lot of times these frameworks will make these primary keys for exist.
很多时候这些框架将把这些主键当为存在的。
And so the primary key is, is a constraint,
所以，主键是一个约束，
that the database management system will enforce for you on your relational data,
数据库管理系统将对你的关系数据强制执行，
make sure that within any given relation,
确保在任何给定关系中，
there does not exist a multiple records with the same primary key.
不存在具有相同主键的多个记录。
Talk about how to do automatic identity columns throughout the semester,
在这个学期讨论如何做自动身份列，
but there's basically ways database system can generate these columns for you.
但是数据系统有方法可以为你生成这些列。
Foreign keys and this is to enforce referential integrity
外键，这是为了强制引用完整性，
to make sure that, if I have a two in one relation,
以确保，如果我有一个二对一的关系，
refers to another tuple, in another relation,
与另一个 tuple 关系关联，
that the database system assessment you, you know, an orphan or or, or a broken,
数据库系统评估一个孤儿或一个坏了的，
because you you delete the record from one row,
因为你从一行中删除了记录，
still a dangley point and another row.
仍然有一个[悬挂点]和另一行。
Going back here to our database,
回到我们的数据库，
in its table.
在它的表中。
But say we have this mix tape here, right,
但是假设我们这里有一盘混音磁带，
we have a bunch of artists appear on it,
我们有一群艺术家出现在上面，
how do we, on this mix tape,
我们该怎么做，在这盘混音磁带上，
and, the for relational support arrays, at least the original version of it.
对于[关系支持数组]，最少是它的原始版本。
So in the data model,
所以，在数据模型中，
do this, you would have a cross reference table,
执行这个操作，你将拥有一个交叉引用表，
where I can keep track of the unique pairs of the relationships between the artists and the albums.
我可以在那里跟踪艺术家和专辑之间独特的关系对。
Right, and now again,
现在，再次，
again, it does it for you,
同样，它会为你做这件事，
so you just write the same delete command,
所以你只需编写相同的删除命令，
the key is not all to do you,
关键并不是为你做事情，
my kind with Python code,
我自己的 Python 代码中，
I'd have to do all that myself in my application code
我必须自己在我的应用程序代码中完成所有这些工作，
to follow those pointers,
跟踪这些指针，
to go find the things I'm looking for,
找到我正在寻找的东西，
to make sure that I don't have these, these dependencies.
确保我没有这些依赖项。
The way you do this is,
你这样做的方式是，
throw errors if, if you're going to violate.
如果违反，抛出错误。
The last, you can have constraints or protection mechanism,
最后，你可以有约束或保护机制，
you can have the data system in force
你可以使强制数据系统，
to make sure that data follows the proper has values that that conform to some kind of domain
以确保数据遵循符合某些域的值，
or that you,
或者，
you don't have values or tuples,
你没有值或 tuple ，
that take you in other things.
给你带来其他东西。
The idea that you can specify for a given attribute or within the global,
可以为指定给定属性或全局的概念，
with a given attribute or given table across multiple tables,
具有给定属性或跨多个表的给定表，
I can have every single time I make a modification
我可以每一次我进行修改，
or any of these constraints being violated,
或任何这些约束被违反，
if if yes, then I throw an error and,
如果是，那么我抛出一个错误，
and I don't let you make make any changes.
不让你做任何改变。
So again, back to the example,
所以，再次回到这个例子，
she brought it before,
她之前提到过的，
well, what if someone writes a string character in your column,
如果有人在你的列中写了一个字符串字符怎么办，
for my CSV file,
对于我的 CSV 文件，
the database system might actually prevent you from doing that,
数据库系统可能会阻止你这样做，
if you had these encounter constraints,
如果你遇到这些约束，
because we would know, okay, you're trying to store something,
因为我们会知道你试图保存一些东西，
try to store a character into an integer column,
试图将字符保存到整型列中，
I can't let you do that, in an error,
我不能让你这样做，并抛出错误，
you can do other things,
你可以执行其他操作，
like make sure that the the year has to be greater than 100 or greater than 0,
如确保年份必须大于 100 或大于 0 ，
and the database system will enforce that for you.
操作系统将为你强制执行这个。
The most common constraints that are out there,
最常见的限制在这里，
things could happen for you,
事情可能会发生在你身上，
and doesn't let you make the change.
不让你做出改变。
But again, we find this in our schema and,
但是再次，我们在我们的方案中发现，
and the original database system is doesn't make sure that the going enforce.
原始的数据库系统是不能确保强制的。
So, now you know matter if you know,
所以现在你知道了，
Python code is [],
Python 代码是[]，
you have to start making changes,
你必须开始做出改变，
they know you know what's going on in the database,
他们知道数据库里发生了什么，
database will prevent you from shooting yourself in the foot
数据库将阻止你[搬起石头砸自己的脚]，
and making changes,
做出改变，
these constraints.
（使用）这些约束。
All right, so now we've got to talk about,
好的，现在我们要谈谈，
how we actually want to interact the database,
我们想要如何与数据库交互，
assuming we set up, we define,
假设我们建立了，我们定义了，
what, what our database and relations are going to look like,
我们的数据库和关系将是什么样子的，
we want to talk about how we actually want to, to run queries on it.
我们想谈谈我们想怎么对其进行查询。
So at a high level,
所以，在比较高的层面上，
there's two basic approaches to do this,
有两种基本的方法来做到这个，
there's the procedural and non-procedural languages,
有过程性语言和非过程性语言，
the, non-procedural one is,
非过程性的是，
where you would say, here's the answer, I want you to compute,
你说，这就是答案，我想让你计算，
I don't know how to compute it, you figure it out.
我不知道怎么算，你自己解决。
So relational calculus and the SQL or relational calculus is going to be non-procedural, declarative,
所以， SQL 或关系型演算是非过程的，声明式的，
we're not going to cover a relational calculus,
我们不会讨论关系演算，
because you don't know it,
因为你不知道它，
you know, I've never used relational calculus, have you,
我从来没有用过关系演算，你用过吗，
never,
从来没有，
only the theory papers, which we're not doing, we don't care about.
只有理论论文，我们不会做，我们不关心。
But it is, it is how it is going to work,
但它是如何工作的方式，
if you're [] putting a query, optimize calculus,
如果你提出一个查询，优化演算，
but in the real world,
但在现实世界中，
but relational algebra is not something,
但关系代数并不是什么东西，
you don't get the program,
你得不到程序，
but this will be,
但这将会是，
we want to to run queries and build execution engine,
我们想要运行查询和建立执行引擎，
all the things we later on.
我们以后要做的事情。
We want to call relational at a high level,
我们在高层次上称为关系，
and then, yes, we'll go over through the,
然后，是的，我们将学习[]，
the course is the modern variance of it.
这门课是它的现代变种。
Alright, so the, relational algebra 1969,
好的，所以关系代数是 1969 年（建立的），
they also define the the algebra that you would use to interact with database system,
他们还定义了用于与数据库系统交互的代数，
and it's the way to extract data from it,
这是从其中提取数据的方法，
and compute answers that you want.
并计算出你想要的答案。
So in original paper, he defined seven fundamental operators,
所以在最初的论文中，他定义了七个基本运算符，
it since,
它一直存在，
it's been additional operations you need in modern applications,
直到在现代应用程序中，你需要更多运算符，
like this doesn't have sorting,
比如，这个没有排序，
and obviously, applications you need sorting, so that came later.
显然，应用程序需要排序，所以后面加入了。
But all this is going to be based on,
但所有这些都将建立在，
to order lists of records or duplicate records,
对重复记录列表排序，
unordered list of tuples, but without any duplicates.
tuple 的无序列表，但是没有重复。
Now, what's been slightly confusing is that,
现在，有一点令人困惑的是，
in, in SQL, by default it's going to try to use bag algebra,
在 SQL 中，默认情况下它会使用袋代数，
which is basically an unordered set, that does have duplicates
这基本上是一个无序集合，有重复的，
or sometimes it's called a multiset,
或者有时它被称为多重集合，
and the reason why SQL wants to use bags instead of sets,
为什么 SQL 想要使用袋而不是集合，
because it's actually you be more efficient,
因为实际上你会更有效率，
if you don't care about removing duplicates later on,
如果你不关心以后删除重复项，
but algebra that we care about here,
但是我们在这里关心的代数，
we assume we're going to get rid of duplicates.
我们假设要去掉重复。
So the basic idea of all these operators is that,
所以所有这些运算符的基本思想是，
you're going take some, some, some relation as your input
你要把一些关系作为你的输入，
or one or more of your inputs
或者你的一个或多个输入，
and then you're, you're going to do some operation on them
然后你要对它们进行一些运算，
and then produce a new relation as the output,
然后产生一个新的关系作为输出，
and you can start chaining all these, these operators together,
你可以开始把所有这些运算符链接在一起，
to do more complex things.
来做更复杂的事情。
So we'll go through each of these one by one.
所以，我们将逐一介绍这些内容。
Animations aren't working, I don't know why,
动画没有工作，我不知道为什么，
but that's okay, showing everything all at once.
但是没有问题，一次展示所有的东西。
First, [] is SELECT,
第一个是 SELECT ，
but I think the original paper calls that restrict thing, right,
但我想原始论文称之为 restrict ，
that you're trying to restrict the tuple
你试图限制 tuple ，
and the idea in your SELECT operator,
在 SELECT 运算符的想法中，
you're going to define first order predicate logic
你将定义一阶谓词逻辑，
to specify what tuple will match,
以指定哪个 tuple 将匹配，
what SELECT operator is trying to do,
SELECT 运算符想要做什么，
it's boolean logic,
这是布尔逻辑，
like something equals something or something less than something,
比如某事等于某事或某事小于某事，
but you can have conjunctions AND or disjunctions OR,
但你可以有逻辑与 AND 或逻辑或 OR ，
on whatever your target table is.
不管你的目标表是什么。
Next operator is PROJECTION,
下一个运算符是 PROJECTION ，
I'm not good at greek symbols,
我不擅长希腊符号，
for this one, it's easy to remember,
对于这个，它很容易记住，
because it's a low pi symbol,
因为它的小写是 pi 符号，
and the idea here,
这里的想法是，
as as your input and specify what you want to be in the output of,
只要你的输入和指定你想要的输出，
of the output of the operator,
运算符的输出，
so you can rearrange the the ordering of the attributes,
这样你就可以重新安排属性的顺序，
you can remove attributes you don't, you don't,
你可以删除（你不需要的）属性，
and then you can manipulate the values of the attributes to to generate derived value,
然后，你可以操作属性的值以生成派生值，
again, but it's only operating on whatever that's given to it,
但它只在任何给它的东西上操作，
to subtract by 100.
减去 100 。
So now we talk,
现在我们讨论，
operators that take that, take multiple relations as their input.
把多重关系作为它们的输入的操作符。
So in the, in the, in the UNION operator, it's a binary operator,
UNION 运算符，它是一个二元运算符，
so you can use operation from set theory,
所以你可以使用集合中的运算，
general relation that contains all tuples,
生成包含包含所有 tuple 的关系，
that either appear on the one relations or both the relations,
出现在一个关系或两个关系上，
so here,
所以在这里。
the UNION calls,
UNION 调用，
so UNION will get in SQL, will get rid of the duplicates,
所以 UNION 加入 SQL ，会去掉重复的，
if you want to keep the duplicates and make it run faster,
如果你想保留复制并使其运行得更快，
you would add its UNION ALL, A L L,
你可以添加 UNION ALL ， A L L ，
we don't have to worry about that.
我们不需要担心这一点。
Just like UNION, we also have INTERSECTION,
就像 UNION 一样，我们也有 INTERSECTION ，
same thing, we can take the take two [],
一样的东西，我们可以使用两个[]，
have to appear.
必须出现。
DIFFERENCE is to take all the two relations
DIFFERENCE 是使用所有两个关系，
and spit out all ones that appear in the first one, but not the second one,
输出在第一个而不在第二个的结果，
and it [], you would use this with the,
你可以使用这个[]，
this basic set theory,
这是基本的集合论，
this is not anything that should be a surprising anyone.
并不应该让任何人感到惊讶。
So any questions before we move on to interesting things?
那么在我们进入有趣的话题之前，还有什么问题吗？
Yeah, so his question is, thank you for bringing this up,
好的，他的问题是，谢谢你提到这个，
the question is,
问题是，
in all these examples so far,
在到目前为止的所有这些示例中，
do the two input relations have to have the exact same schema,
这两个输入关系是否必须具有完全相同的 schema ，
yes, you have to, yes.
是的，你必须[]，是的。
All right, so the next,
好的，接下来，
so if we start looking at how to combine together the relations
我们开始研究如何将这些关系结合在一起，
and [potentially] look at what's actually in the values of them.
并看看它们的值中包含了什么。
So the first one we do is the PRODUCT operator,
所以我们要看的第一个是 PRODUCT 运算符，
or in SQL, it's called the CROSS JOIN,
或者在 SQL 中，它被称为 CROSS JOIN ，
the idea here is that,
这里的想法是，
you're basically going to concatenate the, the first relation and the [] tuple both,
你要连接第一个关系和[] tuple ，
and it's for all unique combinations of tuples
它适用于两个独立的 tuple ，
from the, from one relation and the other,
来自一个关系和另一个关系，
so you're starting to think this as like two for loops, right,
所以你开始想两个 for 循环，
where there's for loops spinning over R,
有 for 循环在 R 上循环，
every single in tuple R,
对于 tuple R 上的每行，
you're going to concatenate with every single tuple S,
你将与 tuple S 的每行连接，
and you,
而且你[]，
I think, I guess why this would actually be useful,
我想，我猜为什么这会真正有用，
why we actually want this.
为什么我们真的想要这样。
I can think of, testing, right,
我能想到的是测试，
if you're trying to find all unique combinations of two inputs
如果你尝试找到两个输入的所有唯一组合
to test some piece of software or some something,
来测试某个软件或某些东西，
then you could use this,
那你就可以用这个，
but beyond that,
但除此之外，
as far as I know, this is not widely used at all,
据我所知，这一点没有被广泛使用，
and oftentimes this shows up,
通常情况下，出现这个，
because you, you make mistake,
因为你出现错误，
like you forgot to WHERE clause
比如你忘了 WHERE 从句，
and, and you get this by accident.
你意外得到了这个。
Or one of the people says, what do you know,
或者其中一个人说，你知道些什么，
what do you mean?
你是什么意思？
Oh yeah, yeah,
哦，是的，
so same as like on enum table where they're trying to like,
比如在枚举表中，他们想要，
but that's like for inputs, right,
但是对于输入，
they get all, trying to get all possible enums as input or something.
他们试图获取所有可能的枚举作为输入或其他内容。
Super useful is to do JOIN,
做 JOIN 非常有用，
and the idea here is that,
这里的想法是，
when you're going to generate the combinations of the, from the two input relations,
当你要产生两个输入关系的组合，
well, [] two tuples you know, it's a binary operator,
[]两个 tuple ，它是一个二元运算符，
there are multi way JOINs,
有多种方式的 JOIN ，
we can take multiple inputs, multiple relations,
我们可以接受多种输入、多种关系，
we can ignore that,
我们可以忽略它，
you want to generate a new output,
你希望生成一个新的输出，
that's going to contain all the tuples,
它将包含所有元组，
that match on the the overlapping attributes in the first relation and the overlapping attributes with the second relation,
与第一个关系中的重叠属性以及与第二个关系的重叠属性相匹配。
so different than the, the INTERSECTION,
与 INTERSECTION 不同，
the INTERSECTION had to have the exact,
INTERSECTION 必须有精确的，
in this case here, I don't have to,
而在这种情况下，我不需要这么做，
I want to find the attributes where they do overlap,
我想找出它们重叠的属性，
I gonna check that.
我去查一下。
And so in my in, in the original relation algebra here,
所以在在原始的关系代数中，
you would actually, you don't show the duplicate columns,
你不会显示重复的列，
like the id from R and the id from S.
比如来自 R 的 id 和来自 S 的 id 。
So there's a bunch different ways to write this in sql,
所以，在 SQL 中有很多不同的编写方法，
there's a NATURAL JOIN keyword in SQL,
在 SQL 中有一个 NATURAL JOIN 关键词，
or if you want,
或者如果你想的话，
like this, that's, that's a way to do it,
就像这样，这是一种方法，
it, it'll make your application look brittle,
它会让你的应用程序看起来很脆弱，
the question is the order of R and S matter in this case,
问题是，在这种情况下， R 和 S 的顺序很重要，
why would it matter?
这有什么关系？
Again, at this point,
在这一点上，
Both of them, yes.
两个都是，是的。
Yes.
好的。
So his question is.
所以他的问题是[]。
So these are the ones that, that or the ones I showed you
这些是我展示给你们的，
with the fundamentals that Ted defined in the late 1970s,
Ted 在 1970 年代末定义的基本运算符，
it got extended with a bunch of additional things,
它被扩展了一些额外的东西，
building real applications,
构建真正的应用程序，
you need more than here in the original relational model, relational algebra, right.
你需要的比原始的关系模型、关系代数中的更多。
Renaming is like a PROJECTION.
Rename 就像 PROJECTION 。
Assignment values or starting assigning attributes to, to, to, important.
Assignment 将值分配给[]，很重要。
Duplicate Elimination distinct clauses, that.
Duplicat Elimination 不同的子句[]。
Used to teach it, we don't teach anymore,
过去教它，现在我们不再教了，
because you never find it.
因为你永远找不到它。
Basically a way Division,
Division 是一种方式，
a way to find, find the tuple run relation that matches all tuples in another relation,
查找与另一个关系中的所有 tuple 匹配的运行关系的 tuple ，
it doesn't appear in the real world, it's not common,
它不会出现在现实世界中，这并不常见，
we don't have to worry it.
我们也不用担心它。
About it the again,
总结一下，
the core of every relational data system would be built on, on these, on these, on this algebra,
每个关系数据系统的核心都将建立在这些代数上，
and then we can define a,
然后我们可以定义一个，
around the sort of,
围绕着一种，
that allow us to support very expressive, very complex SQL queries.
使我们能够支持非常有表现力、非常复杂的 SQL 查询。
So why do we need,
那么我们为什么需要，
because you can find a Duplicate Elimination on the primary key.
因为你可以在主键上找到 Duplicate Elimination 。
So, the, relational algebra query still, you know, piece of software,
所以，关系代数查询仍然是软件的一部分，
the system to actually execute it,
一个系统来执行它，
very,
非常，
so one order versus another,
一个顺序对比另一个，
so say I do, where, where, where the S,
比如我做， where S ，
to tuples together, billion, one billion tuples together, right away, right.
马上到十亿 tuple 一起。
So relational algebra show specifying basically how you want the data system to execute things,
所以，关系代数展示的是指定你希望数据系统如何执行操作，
so a better approach,
一种更好的方法，
and this is motivation,
这是[]的激励，
is that, we want to tell the database system,
是我们想告诉数据库系统，
here's the answer we want,
这是我们想要的答案，
we don't know how, we don't care how you're actually going to us,
我们不知道，我们不在乎你如何去为我们找，
but this is what we want you to do for us,
但这就是我们希望你为我们做的，
instead of specifying the exact algebra steps,
不是精确的代数步骤，
I want the computer, hey, retrieve the tuples from R and S,
我想要计算机获取 R 和 S 的 tuple ，
and find me all those where b_id,
帮我找出所有在 b_id 的，
and then now the data system can can take into account,
然后数据系统可以考虑，
how the data is being stored, what kind of,
数据是如何存储的，是哪种类型的数据，
where things are actually physically located,
数据实际所在的物理位置，
what the CPU can support,
什么样 CPU 能支持，
what kind of cpu do I have,
我的 CPU 是什么类型的，
do I have a GPU,
我有 GPU 吗，
do have an FPGA,
有没有 FPGA ，
do I have other things,
我还有其他东西吗，
all of that can be,
所有这些可以，
in its decision for how to execute the query one way versus another.
决定如何以这种方式执行查询，而不是以另一种。
Now, again, think of like if I'm a developer,
现在，再想一想，如果我是一名开发人员，
I can write a bunch of code in my laptop,
我可以在我的笔记本电脑上编写一堆代码，
writes some sql on my little test database,
编写一些 SQL 在我的小测试数据库，
and then the same sql statement will then work exactly the same,
然后相同的 SQL 语句将完全相同地工作，
or it also produce the same correct result,
或者它也会产生相同的正确结果，
when I deploy in production on, you know, a giant machine that has a lot of memory,
当我在具有大量内存的巨型计算机上进行生产部署时，
and I don't have to change my application code,
而且我不需要更改我的应用程序代码，
so that's the beauty,
这就是它的美妙之处，
that's the beauty of why you're going to want to declare language,
这就是为什么你会想要声明语言的原因，
but the, the core concept of how that declarative language are going to work
但是，声明性语言如何工作的核心概念，
is predicated on relational algebra.
是在关系代数基础上预测的。
So SQL is going to be the de facto standard,
所以， SQL 成为事实上的标准，
as we discuss.
正如我们所讨论的。
Okay?
好的？
Quick, before we go, I want to talk about other data models.
在我们结束之前，我想快速谈谈其他数据模型。
And because vector database is the hot thing on hacker news,
因为矢量数据库是黑客新闻上的热门话题，
it's worth discussing what they actually are,
值得讨论它们到底是什么，
so you guys understand why it's all you see, you see it in the real world.
你们明白为什么你可以在现实世界中看到它。
So document data model is old,
所以文档数据模型是老的，
so MongoDB came out 2008 all this groundbreaking,
MongoDB 在 2008 年问世，这一切都是开创性的，
we're storing things as json,
我们是以 json 的形式存储东西，
but the ideas go back to the 1980s early 1990s,
但这种想法可以追溯到 1980 年代， 1990 年代初，
they were object, object-oriented programming was the hot thing,
面向对象编程是热门的东西，
so people said rather than storing things of relations,
所以人们说，与其存储东西的关系，
we want to store things as as objects,
不如像存储对象一样存储东西，
and then they had these sort of specialized programming languages,
然后他们有了这些专门的编程语言，
that knew how to write, write code in your like in,
知道如何写写代码，就像在，
it would, database system.
它会[]，数据库系统。
But those they're basically those objects are the same thing as json,
但是那些对象和 json 是一样的，
they're the same thing as xml,
它们和 xml 是一样的，
xml databases were the hot thing in the late 90s, 2000s,
xml 数据库是 90 年代末， 2000 年的热门事物，
so at a high level, they are equivalent.
但是在高级别上，它们是对等的。
So that, it's a hierarchical data structure,
所以，它是一种分层数据结构，
we have these named fields,
我们有这些命名字段，
and the values of the named fields can be an array, a scalar type and that,
并且命名字段的值可以是数组、标量类型或其他，
and again, all the modern systems use use json.
所有的现代系统都使用 json 。
So now the reason why these, these document database systems exist is
所以为什么这些文档数据库系统存在的原因是，
this this problem that comes up called the impedance mismatch,
这个叫做阻抗不匹配的问题的出现，
that's, that's the problem of
这里的问题是，
if I break my, my, my data up into these different relations,
如果我把我的数据分解成这些不同的关系，
but I write my application code in like Python or whatever in in objects,
但我使用比如 Python 或其他面向对象来编写我的应用程序代码，
now when I want to go retrieve data from the,
现在，当我想要检索数据时，
it bunch of joins stitch together my,
有很多 JOIN 一起，
is the form that I want to operate on my application,
我想要在我的应用程序上操作，
but the database wants [] or separate.
但数据库想要[]或者分开。
And so the.
所以。
And I would argue, yeah, for some things that makes sense,
我会争辩说，是的，有些事情是合理的，
but for other things, it's actually a bad idea,
但在其他方面，这实际上是一个坏主意，
because now you're gonna have a bunch of duplicate data,
因为现在你会有一堆重复的数据，
you have all the problems we solved before,
你有我们以前解决的所有问题，
where I got to make sure that if I change, change, something that's duplicated in a file in my database,
我要确保如果我改变在我的数据库的文件中重复的东西，
I make the changes all over the place.
我会在所有地方进行改变。
So we go back to our example before of the,
所以我们回到前面的例子，
so the high level,
所以高级别上，
if I have an object,
如果我有一个对象，
I once again for a given artist,
为某个给定的艺术家，
here's all the albums that they appear on,
这是他们出现在上面的所有专辑，
now, you can do this in a single SQL statement,
现在，你可以在一条 SQL 语句中做到这一点，
but yeah,
但是，是的，
it's not perfect,
这不是完美的，
but, it's, there's ways on it.
但是，是有办法的。
So the document data model say,
所以文档数据模型说，
you don't need this guy here of this
你这里不需要这个，
and if your application code is,
如果你的应用程序代码是，
and same problem as before,
和以前一样的问题，
like if I, if artists appearing on the same album,
如果艺术家出现在同一张专辑中，
I could have duplicate entries in all their json documents,
我可能会在他们的所有 json 文档中有重复的条目，
and if I make updates,
如果我更新了，
gotta make sure I change, change all of them.
我必须确保我改变了所有的。
So.
所以。
And so, natively.
所以，从本质上说。
So the interesting inflection point in the database marketplace,
所以，数据库市场出现了有趣的拐点，
where almost all the, the, the json databases that said,
几乎所有的 JSON 数据库都说，
we don't want to use SQL,
我们不想使用 SQL ，
we don't want to use relational data model,
我们不想使用关系数据模型，
a lot of them have basically converged and become more relational like,
他们中的许多已经汇聚在一起，变得更像是关系型，
and you can run, you can write SQL on [].
你可以运行，你可以在[]上写 SQL 。
And so over time,
随着时间的推移，
what we're seeing is that,
我们看到的是，
the intellectual difference between document database, sql databases, and relational databases has, has shrunk,
文档数据库、 SQL 数据库和关系数据库之间的智力差异已经缩小，
and now basically they're all relational databases,
现在，它们基本上都是关系数据库，
Mongo was the last holdout,
Mongo 是最后一个抵抗的，
Mongo added support for SQL in 2021, right,
Mongo 在 2021 年增加了对 SQL 的支持，
but for years, because we know the founders are like,
但多年来，因为我们知道创始人说，
oh, we're never going to support SQL,
哦，我们永远不会支持 SQL ，
they do,
他们这样做，
and then get,
然后得到[]，
they also support json.
它们还支持 JSON 。
So I go to the, document database that is contorting stuff,
所以我认为文档数据库是扭曲的东西，
look like relational database when you just database [Postgres].
当你只是数据库 Postgres 时，它看起来像是关系数据库。
They're in the news, because obviously ChatGPT is the hot thing,
他们出现在新闻中，是因为显然 ChatGPT 是热门话题，
and so the, the way to think about this now is like the,
所以，思考这件事的方式是，
in when pure web applications 10, 15 years ago,
10 15 年前，在纯 Web 应用程序中，
everything was always json,
一切都是 json ，
therefore, I need a json database
所以，我需要一个 JSON 数据库，
and that's how the NoSQL systems got started,
NoSQL 系统就是这样开始的，
now it's like, OK, well I have all this, this, these these vectors back
现在就像，好的，我有所有这些向量回来，
from from from transformer ChatGPT or whatever I'm using,
来自 transformer ChatGPT 或无论我使用的什么，
store that in a database, that can natively store vectors,
把它存储在一个可以原生存储向量的数据库中，
so I can do,
所以我可以这样做，
and I would argue that these systems they, they're, they're limited the functionality
我会争辩说，这些系统它们的功能有限，
and over time they're basically going to have to morph to a relational database.
随着时间的推移，它们将不得不转变为一个关系型数据库。
So the vector data model vector is just a, right,
所以向量数据模型，向量只是一个，
that and in in this approach here with case,
在这种情况下，
it's a one dimensional array of floating point numbers,
它是一个一维的浮点数数组，
and the system going,
整个系统都在，
neighbor search either exact or approximate
邻居搜索可以是精确搜索，也可以是近似搜索，
to allow you to semantic search over your data,
让你可以对数据进行语义搜索，
so in all my predates I showed before,
所以在我之前展示的所有早期数据中，
it's like a_id equals 2, a_id equals 102 whatever,
比如 a_id 等于 2 ， a_id 等于 102 ，
the exact matches,
精确匹配，
but these vectors allow you to embed somehow magically through, through, through transformers,
但这些向量允许你嵌入数据神奇地通过转换器，
a deeper meaning of what your data actually looks like,
一种你的数据的样子的更深层含义，
so you can ask higher level questions like,
所以你可以问更高层次的问题，
hey, show me, you know, show me things related to this, you know,
比如，给我看看与这个相关的东西，
instead of doing exact matches for the keyword CMU,
不是做关键字 CMU 的精确匹配，
I would I would, I can learn things like, oh,
我可以学习这样的东西，
talk about a university in in Pittsburgh that was [] of by,
谈谈匹兹堡的一所大学，它是[]，
like you can learn things about,
就像你可以了解，
that are implicit in the data rather than doing exact lookup.
数据中隐含的东西，而不是进行精确的查找。
Yes.
是的。
The question is what's [interesting] graph databases and vector databases,
问题是什么是图形数据库和矢量数据库，
let's take that one [], that's different,
让我们把它[]，这是不同的，
but vectors literally just a one like one dimensional arrays,
但是向量从字面上来说只是一个一维的数组，
graph databases are storing the relationship between objects
图形数据库存储对象之间的关系，
like edges and nodes and things like that.
比如边和节点等东西。
If you're looking at one degree from the current node, it sounds like it's similar,
如果你从当前节点看一个度数，它听起来很相似，
but, but like the, how to say this,
但是，比如，这个该怎么说，
in a graph database, you're explicitly storing that structure
在图形数据库中，你显式地存储该结构，
and you're traversing it to find things that you're looking for,
你遍历它以找到正在寻找的东西，
this is like I'm encoding it as a vector
这就像我把它编码成一个向量，
and I don't know what the vector is actually representing.
而我不知道这个向量实际上代表了什么。
So Pinecone, a bunch of,
所以 Pinecone ，很多[]，
gave a talk with us two years ago,
两年前给我们做了一次演讲，
in two weeks,
两周后，
so if you want to learn more about this, check it out.
所以如果你想更多地了解这一点，请查看。
At their core, all these vector databases are just going to be a,
在它们的核心，所有这些矢量数据库将只是一个，
index, a lot to do, nearest neighbor search, right,
索引，很多最近的邻居搜索要做，
so sort of looks like this,
所以看起来就像这样，
interpret these things, right,
正确地解释这些东西，
it numbers, the need never it out,
数字，不需要它出现，
we don't know what it is,
我们不知道这是什么，
as my ranked list.
作为我的排名表。
That's the core at a super high level of what a vector database is doing.
这是在高级别上，矢量数据库所做的核心。
Question, is this similar to relational calculus,
问题，这类似于关系演算吗，
what is, what part of this,
这是什么意思，哪一部分，
well,
好的，
or we,
或者我们，
I'm just trying to them,
我只是在试着让他们，
they care about,
他们关心的是，
so I would argue,
所以我会争辩说，
the core these are is just this,
这些问题的核心就在于，
no, right,
不是，
you can do a bunch of databases. They all added this,
你可以做一堆数据库，他们都加了这个，
has pgvector SingleStore Clickhouse,
有 pgvector SingleStore Clickhouse ，
beyond all for, now.
就目前而言，这是最重要的。
Okay.
好的。
I just want to expose to you to see.
我只是想展示给你看。
So, databases are ubiquitous,
所以，数据库是无处不在的，
relational algebra defines the primitive database system
关系代数定义了数据库系统原语，
and then relational algabra will be the the core, do these interactions
关系代数是[]的核心，进行这些交互，
and then that'll define how we want to build the component of our system to, to, to run queries.
然后就定义了我们希望如何构建系统组件来运行查询。
So Wednesday's class will be on on SQL,
所以周三的课将在 SQL 上，
project zero is out,
项目0已经放出了，
Please start it now, it's due the 11th
请现在就开始，截止时间是 11 号，
and then homework one will be out.
然后家庭作业1也放出了。
Hit it.
开始吧。